Guide to the Aden Field Papers, 1940s-2015 and undated RL.11346
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Aden Field papers
1940s-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Field, Aden
RL.11346
48 Linear Feet
Aden Field is an author and poet from Durham, North Carolina, who co-founded the Regulator along with other Durham community organizations. This collection consists of his journals, writings, postcard collections, community projects and files, and his collection of correspondence and writings from friends and family. It documents his friendships and relationships, Durham community events and activities, and his career as a writer and teacher in North Carolina.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into series: Journals, Postcard Binders, Writings, Businesses and Projects, Name and Correspondence Files, and Personal Materials.
Biographical / Historical
Aden Field is an author, playwright, and poet based in Durham, North Carolina. He was born in 1938 in McKenzie, Tennessee, and graduated from Harvard University in 1959. Field attended Duke University until 1966, when he withdrew from courses but stayed in Durham. He and several friends co-founded The Regulator bookshop in 1976, located on Ninth Street in Durham. Field also helped found and manage groups and publications such as Urban Hiker, WDBS Guide, Black Mountain Project, and Collaborations of the Creative and the Sacred, Inc.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Aden Field Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016.
Collection Overview
This collection includes Field's correspondence, writings, journals, postcard binders, and files from his management and work at The Regulator, Collaborations, Black Mountain Project, Urban Hiker, and several local arts councils and youth writing programs. Materials have been sorted into series but largely remain labeled and foldered according to Field's own arrangement scheme.
Field's Journals Series contain incredibly detailed chapters of his life, which were created and re-typed by Field as a project in the 1990s. Early journals are volumes 1-4; he began titling them in the 1980s. Entries include his daily activities, Durham news, horoscope (I Ching), financial spending, and introspective analysis of his thoughts, writings, and relationships. Binders are dated and sorted by date, YYMMDD.
Field's postcard binders project began in the 1990s to assemble a Book of Men, featuring postcards of images of men in art from art galleries around the world. Other binders he created included postcards documenting American society and culture from the nineteenth century through the 1990s. He also created a Book of Women and collected assorted postcards that remain unassembled into binders, all held in this series.
Field's writings range from poetry to plays to prose, and the Writings Series includes drafts and published versions arranged in both chronological and alphabetical files. The chron files are dated YYMMDD. The alphabetical files are arranged by title.
Field's many businesses and projects are sorted by group name, with some groups' files containing only one or two items and some groups filling an entire box (see especially Collaborations, The Regulator, and Urban Hiker). These files include correspondence, publications, board minutes, notes by Field, and account ledgers. Field served as treasurer for many Durham organizations. Personal tax and investment information has been removed when identified.
The Name and Correspondence Files document Field's personal relationships and his communications as an author and community activist. Files are not strictly correspondence; some include artwork, writings, and publications, including zines and newsletters. Materials are filed by author/creator.
Finally, Field's personal materials include childhood and adolescent scrapbooks and yearbooks; photographs and snapshots with friends and family; headshots and portraits of Field; and personal accounting and financial ledgers.
Poets, American -- 20th century -- Diaries; Drama -- Studying and teaching -- North Carolina -- Durham; Independent bookstores -- North Carolina; Zines -- United States -- Periodicals; Authors, American -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Durham (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; Gay men -- Poetry; Gay men -- Southern States; Art -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; The Regulator
- Journals, 1954-2015
  - Early Days / Vol. 1, 1954 - 1974; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Vol. 2, 1961 - 1965; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Trip log, 1962 (Box 31)
  - Vol. 3, 1965 - 1967; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Vol. 4, 1967 - 1968; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Vol. IV, 1968 Oct. 7 - 1969 Sept. 3; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Untitled journal, 1969 Apr. 1 - 1969 Sept. 7 (Box 1)
  - Vol. IV: Continuation at Dawnhouse, 1969 Sept. 10 - 1969 Nov. 2 (Box 1)
  - Quaker Days, 1970 Jun. 19 - 1973 Sept. 19; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Germination: The Smaller Image, 1973 Oct. 3 - 1974 Feb. 15; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Savannah: The Pool of Reflection, 1974 Sept. 13 - 1975 Jun. 15; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Vines: The Fountain of the Will, 1st Part, 1975 Jun. 15 - 1976 Feb. 13; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Vines: The Fountain of the Will, 1975 Jun. 15 - 1977 Feb. 24; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Moving & A New Place, 1977 Mar. 1 - 1979 May 6; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - The Texture of Time, 1979 May 8 - 1981 May 24; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Untitled diary, 1979 (Box 31)
  - Modulations, 1981 May 24 - 1982 Aug. 14; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Determination, 1982 Aug. 14 - 1983 Mar. 4; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Touching His Heart, 1983 Mar. 6 - 1984 Feb. 24; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Gardening the Self, 1984 Feb. 24 - 1987 Sept. 11; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - A Nominal Veil, 1987 (Box 31)
  - A Book of the House, 1987 (Box 31)
  - Two Books - Part 1, 1987 Sept. 12 - 1988 Mar. 23 (Box 3)
  - Two Books - Part 2, 1987 Sept. 12 - 1988 Apr. 23; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - The Pablican / Dread-Full Aftermath, 1988 Apr. 8 - 1990 Jun. 15; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Subduction, 1990 Jun. 18 - 1992 Feb. 15; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Finding Family, 1992 Feb. 19 - 1992 Sept. 25; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - The Secret Name, 1992 Sept. 26 - 1993 Feb. 1 (Box 3)
  - Eros, or Myself - Whirlpool of Feelings, 1993 Jan. - 1995 Jun.; 3 folders (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Photograph album
  - Returning to my Heart, 1993 Feb. 3 - 1993 Sept. 19; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Poking in the Rag Bag / Summoning the God, 1993 Sept. 20 - 1994 Mar. 11; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Savannah Days, 1994 July 18 - 1994 Oct. 16; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Pow-Wow-ism, 1994 Oct. 17 - 1995 Mar. 14; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Fast Moving Water, 1995 Mar. 22 - 1995 Nov. 3; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Watershed Views, 1995 Nov. 4 - 1996 Apr. 20; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Naming the River, 1996 Apr. 22 - 1996 Dec. 8; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Crossing the River, 1996 Dec. 12 - 1997 Mar. 27; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - New Country, 1997 Mar. 28 - 1998 Feb. 3; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - A Falling Veil / Alone and Gone, 1998 Feb. 4 - 1998 Dec. 11; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Image Opens / Image Constrained, 1998 Dec. 21 - 1999 Aug. 21; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Opening Windows, 1999 Aug. 21 - 1999 Dec. 27; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Discipline / Hiatus / The Spoiled, 2000 Jan. 3 - 2001 Jan. 20; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Caesura: Crash, 2000 Apr. 4 (Box 5)
  - Leccioines, 2001 Jan. 22 - 2001 Aug. 21; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - The Uses of Surprise, 2001 Aug. 22 - 2002 Feb. 16; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Healing, 2002 Feb. 17 - 2002 May 7; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Loosening Up, 2002 Nov. 27 - 2003 Jul. 15; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - New Regimens, 2003 July 21 - 2004 Jan. 30 (Box 6)
  - The Book of Re-Generations, 2003 (Box 31)
  - Ocean of Change, 2004 Feb. 7 - 2004 Aug. 25; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Going Where?, 2004 Sept. 3 - 2005 Feb. 24; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Balance, 2005 Feb. 26 - 2005 Sept. 10; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Veering, 2005 Sept. 13 - 2005 Dec. 20; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - The Borderland, 2005 Dec. 21 - 2006 Apr. 30; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Hunting and Gathering, 2006 May 4 - 2006 Aug. 8; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Tracking, 2006 Aug. 10 - 2006 Dec. 24; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Roaming, 2006 Dec. 26 - 2007 Aug. 3; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Studying Things, 2007 Aug. 5 - 2007 Oct. 27; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Vacancies, 2007 Oct. 27 - 2008 Feb. 6; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Botanical Year (excerpts), 2007 (Box 31)
  - Snakes and Ladders, 2008 Feb. 7 - 2008 May 8 (Box 7)
  - Momentos, 2008 May 9 - 2008 Sept. 9; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - The Revenant / Open Highway, 2008 Sept. 10 - 2008 Nov. 17; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Distant Objects, 2008 Nov. 18 - 2009 Feb. 7; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - A Digital Man, 2009 Feb. 7 - 2009 July 16; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - A New Journey, 2009 July 20 - 2009 Dec. 30; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - A Prelude to Brazil, 2009 Dec. 30 - 2010 Jan. 15; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Open Landscape, 2010 Jan. 15 - 2010 Aug. 10; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - The Forms of Seeking, 2010 Aug. 15 - 2010 Dec. 15; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Further Seeking, 2010 Dec. 16 - 2011 Apr. 20; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Computer Woes, 2011 Apr. 21 - 2011 Sept. 11; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Intuition, 2011 Sept. 12 - 2011 Dec. 22; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - New Year, 2011 Dec. 25 - 2012 Apr. 15; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - After-Math, 2012 Apr. 15 - 2012 Nov. 14; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Caesura, 2012 Nov. 15 - 2013 Jul. 24; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Untitled Pages, 2013 Jan (Box 9)
  - Reflection, 2013 Jul. 26 - 2014 Nov. 13; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Untitled mss Pages, 2013 Dec. 5 - 2015 Mar. (Box 9)
  - The Mirror of Erised: A Commonplace Book (Box 9)
  - Mentors and Advisers: A Commonplace Book (Box 9)
  - Eros, or Myself: A Commonplace Book, 1994 Mar. 17 - 1994 Apr. 7; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Eros, or Myself: For Adam, 1994 Mar. 17 - 1994 Apr. 7 (Box 9)
  - Eros, or Myself: For Joseph, 1994 Apr. 8 - 1995 Jul. 3; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Addendum: The Poetry Notebooks, Volume 1, Before 1977; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Addendum: The Poetry Notebooks, Volume 2, 1977 - 1991 (Box 9)
  - Addendum: The Poetry Notebooks, Volume 3, 1991 - 2003; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - General Index, 1970s - 2005; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Journal work sheets, 1969 (Box 31)
  - Untitled diary pages, 1969-1970 (Box 31)
  - Assorted journal entries, 1960s-1993 (Box 31)
  - Assorted journal entries, 2000s (Box 31)
  - Various pages, 2007 (Box 31)
- Postcard Binders, 1990s-2000s
  - The Book of Men: An Eccentric History of the World, 1994; 8 folders (Box 11)
    3 binders, disbound (3 versions of Book of Men binder).
  - The Book of Men: Volume 1, Olden Times (3500 BC-1550 AD), 2 folders (Box 11)
  - The Book of Men: An Eccentric History of the World, Appendices, Part 2, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - The Nineteenth Century: The 1850's (Box 11)
  - The Nineteenth Century: The 1870's, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - The Nineteenth Century: The 1880's, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Women: 1880's-1950's, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - The Nineteenth Century: 1890's, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - The Twentieth Century, Section 2: 1900's (Box 12)
  - The Twentieth Century: The 1910's, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - The Twentieth Century: The 1920's, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - The Twentieth Century: The 1930's, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - The Twentieth Century: The 1940's, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - The Twentieth Century: The 1950's, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - The World We've Got: The 1960's, 8 folders (Box 13)
  - The World We've Got: The 1970's, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - The World We've Got: The 1980's, 7 folders (Box 13)
  - The World We've Got: The 1990's, 9 folders (Box 14)
  - Parallels of Latitude, 1998; 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Glamor, Anti-Glamor, and Reports: A Book with Many Images of Women, 2004; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Assorted postcards (Binder 1), 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Assorted postcards (Binder 2), 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Assorted postcards (Binder 3), 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Photographics: The Canon (Binder 4) (Box 15)
  - Postcards and photographs (Binder 5) (Box 15)
  - Postcards and photographs (Binder 6), 3 folders (Box 15)
- Businesses and Project Files
  - The Aliens Collaboration, 1975 (Box 27)
  - Ambo-Dexters, 1982; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - American Natural Foods, 1977-1983 (Box 27)
  - Art Books shelf list (Box 27)
  - Atlanta Art Papers, Inc.: Art Papers, Vol. 13, Number 5, 1989 (Box 19)
  - Black Mountain Project, 1984-1987; 9 folders (Box 27)
  - Blue Ridge Discovery Center, 2008-2010; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Book of Men materials, 1994, 2005; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - "The Bully and the Hot Dog Man," comic, undated (Box 27)
  - Carolina Friends School youth writing programs, 1990s (Box 27)
  - Carolina Training Association, 1980 (Box 27)
  - Collaborations in the Creative and the Sacred, Inc., 1980-1990s (Box 30)
    This box contains board minutes, correspondence, financial accounts, grant application materials, photographs, and other materials from the administration, group meetings, and retreats led or sponsored by Collaborations.
  - Duke Gay Alliance, 1974 (Box 27)
  - Duke Young Writers, 1992-1998 (Box 27)
  - Durham Arts Council, 1989-1994; 3 folders (Box 27)
  - Eno journals, 1976-1978 (Box 27)
  - Green Ink invoices and expenses, 2008; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Green Ink, misc., 1979-1980s, undated (Box 31)
  - I Ching, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Marian Roh/ Wellspring copyright case, 2000 (Box 27)
  - NC Anvil reviews, 1967 (Box 27)
  - NC Arts Council, 1990; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - "Project 9" NC geology project, 1987-1990s; 5 folders (Box 27)
  - Randolph Arts Guild, 1995-1996 (Box 28)
  - Reading lists (Box 28)
  - Recipes (miscellaneous) (Box 28)
  - The Regulator bookshop administrative and legal materials, 1976-1995; 3 folders (Box 28)
    Board minutes, notes, and legal documents about the founding and expansion of Durham's Regulator bookshop.
  - The Regulator bookshop financial materials, 1970s-1990s; 33 folders (Box 28)
    Field's ledgers and notes from The Regulator bookshop and its parent company, Top of the Ninth, including income and expense reports and other financial tracking materials, largely dating from the 1980s and early 1990s.
  - The Regulator Community Fund/Helen Whiting Scholarship Fund, 1988-2009; 21 folders (Box 28)
    Materials documenting The Regulator's fundraising and sponsorship of scholarships and local Durham community organizations, through the Community Fund and the Helen Whiting memorial Scholarship Fund.
  - The Regulator: Carologue, 1972 (Box 19)
  - Scanner Darkly, 1993 (Box 28)
  - Sister Cities of Durham, Inc., 1992-2011; 9 folders (Box 28, Box 29)
  - Somethyme, Inc. bankruptcy, 1993 (Box 29)
  - "Tao: A New Way of Thinking" text, 1975 (Box 29)
  - The Tao of Power (R.L. Wing), undated; 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Town of Cary: Page-Walker Center workshops, 1996-1997 (Box 29)
  - Triangle Nomad, 1992 (Box 29)
  - Urban Hiker, Inc., 1999-2004; 30 folders (Box 29)
    Includes correspondence, financial materials, and production notes from Field's role in the founding and publication of Urban Hiker magazine. Also contains complete issues of Urban Hiker from July 2003-December 2004.
  - Val's Place, Inc., 1985; 2 folders (Box 29)
  - WDBS Guide, 1977-1979; 7 folders (Box 29)
- Writings
  - Chronological writings files, 1961 Jan - 1979 Dec. 15 (Box 16)
  - Chronological writings files, 1981 Mar. 8 - 2000 Sep. 21 (Box 17)
  - Chronological writings files, 2000 Oct. 1 - 2011 Aug. 18 (Box 18)
  - Alphabetical writings files, A-M, 1960s-2010s (Box 24)
    Manuscripts, research, drafts, and final versions of Field's poems, plays, and prose. Titles include: Ajose; The Bathtub Caper; The Bobber-Cat (zine); The Caldron of Story; Coffee, Beer, Never Fear; the Duke University Yearbook (Vol. 63, 1975); The End of the World Brain; Germination; Eros, or Myself; The Mercy.
  - Alphabetical writings files, M-S, 1960s-2010s (Box 25)
    Manuscripts, drafts, research, and final versions of Field's poems, plays, and prose. Titles included in this box: A Morris Dance; Obvious Knowledge; The Plenum; Savannah: The Pool of Reflection; The Secret Name; Soft Changes; Something's Up/The Princess and the Nemo; A Southern Friendship.
  - Alphabetical writings files, S-V, 1960s-2010s (Box 26)
    Manuscripts, drafts, research, and final versions of Field's poems, plays, and prose. Titles in this box include: Spaces; Star-Gazer; Travelling from Goveen; Vacant Dreams; Vines: The Fountain of the Will.
  - Various manuscript pages, drafts, 1978-2000s (Box 26)
  - Poetry drafts binder, 1975 (Box 26)
  - Reading copy binder, prose, 1992, 1994 (Box 26)
  - Correction copy binder of poems, 1966-1994 and undated (Box 26)
  - Works-in-Progress binder with drafts and outlines, 1984; 2 folders (Box 26)
- Name and Correspondence Files, 1950s-2010s
  - A-F, 1950s-2010s (Box 21)
    Includes correspondence, artwork, and writings by Field's friends, lovers, and relatives. Notable files include the Broughton family, Lawrence Bullock, Mark Cunningham (including several files of original artwork), Guy Davenport, Andre Fernandes, and Aden's parents, the Fields.
  - Bamberger, Bill, 2007 (Box 32)
    Publication: Stories of Home and the Mobile Gallery
  - Cunningham, Mark (oversize artwork), undated (Box 19)
  - F-P, 1950s-2010s (Box 22)
    Includes correspondence, writings, artwork, and publications from Field's friends, lovers, and family. Notable names in this box include Field's parents, Maggie Henniss, Scott and Justine Jackson-Ricketts, and Gioia and Everett Palmieri. Also includes zine titles Mineshaft (filed under Palmieri, the authors) and Free Fan Zines, and drafts of Royal Sorceress (by Justine Jackson-Ricketts) and The Dog Man (by Barry Jacobs).
  - Jackson-Ricketts, Scott (photographs), 1980s; 4 folders (Box 31)
  - P-Z, 1950s-2010s (Box 23)
    Includes correspondence, writings, and artwork from Field's family, friends, and lovers. Notable names in this box include Rich Robeson, Rebecca Ranson, V.C. Rogers (including a copy of Peripheral Visions, his cartoons), and Worth (Buzz) and Susan Weller.
  - Philip (oversize artwork), 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 20)
    Canvas boards painted by Philip (last name uncertain) between 1975 and 1976.
  - General (unsorted) correspondence, 1960s-2010s; 9 folders (Box 23)
- Personal Materials, 1940s-2010s
  - Family photograph album, 1940s-1960s (Box 19)
  - Childhood scrapbook, 1940s-1965 (Box 20)
  - Field's personal stocks/investment ledger, 1993-2000 (Box 15)
  - Field's ledgers and accounts, 1995-1999, 2001, 2008; 7 folders (Box 15, Box 31)
  - McKenzie High School Rebel (yearbooks), 1951-1954; 2 folders (Box 31)
  - Harvard University, 320 Volume (yearbook), 1956 (Box 31)
  - Harvard University Register (yearbook), 1959 (Box 31)
  - Press coverage of Field, 1959-1996; 7 folders (Box 31)
  - Family photographs, 1937-1951 (Box 32)
  - Millington High School press, photographs, 1961-1965 (Box 32)
  - Durham photographs, postcards, 1960s-1970s (Box 32)
  - Cattail Rustication photographs, 1968-1970 (Box 32)
  - Portraits/headshots of Field, 1958-2000s and undated; 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Slides (snapshots), 1980-1983; 6 folders (Box 32)
  - Photographs, in Maine, 1993 (Box 32)
  - Photographs and postcards, in Port Townsend, 1993, 1999-2000, undated (Box 32)
  - Photographs, in Colorado, 1996-1997 (Box 32)
  - Photographs, assorted, 1995-1997, 2000-2003; 5 folders (Box 32)
  - Photographs, Broughton family in Memphis, Colorado, 1970s-1990s (Box 32)
  - Field's bulletin board, with clippings, cards, and photographs (Box 32)